A Finding Aid to the Stephen Poleskie Papers and Chiron Press Records, 1961-2020, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Stephen Poleskie papers and Chiron Press records
1961-2020
bulk 1963-1968
Archives of American Art
Poleskie, Steve, 1938-
AAA.polestep
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The Stephen Poleskie papers and Chiron Press records measure 1.0 linear feet and date from circa 1961-2020, with the bulk from 1963-1968. Stephen (Steve) Poleskie was a painter and printmaker in New York. From 1963 to 1968 he operated Chiron Press, New York City's first fine art screen printing studio. A bulk of this collection includes business correspondence and financial documents as well as writings, printed materials, photographic materials, and digital video recordings that document Poleskie's own career as an artist as well as the activities of Poleskie's Chiron Press.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen (Steve) Poleskie (1938-2019) was a painter and printmaker in New York. From 1963 to 1968 he operated Chiron Press, New York City's first fine art screen printing studio. In 1968, Poleskie sold Chiron Press and became a professor of studio art at Cornell University from 1968 until his retirement in 2000. Poleskie was also a skilled pilot and would create art while flying and trailing smoke, the performance of which he coined, Aerial Theater.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Poleskie papers and Chiron Press records measure 1.0 linear feet and date from circa 1961-2020, with the bulk from 1963-1968. The collection documents Poleskie's own career as an artist as well as the activities of Poleskie's Chiron Press, New York City's first fine art screen printing studio. The collection includes personal and business correspondence with artists, dealers, collectors, and curators; business and financial records; legal documents; notes and writings by Poleskie; clippings, news articles, catalogs, a copy of The Paris Review, preparatory materials for screen prints; photographic materials which includes a photograph of Elaine de Kooning; and digital video recordings related to works by Poleskie.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2022 by Jeanne Mackin, Stephen Poleskie's widow.
Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Educators -- New York (State); Pilots; Printing industry; Interviews; Video recordings; Chiron Press
- Stephen Poleskie papers and Chiron Press records, 1961-2020; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1, OV 2
  Scope and Contents
  The collection includes personal and business correspondence with artists, dealers, collectors, and curators; business and financial records; legal documents; notes and writings by Poleskie; clippings, news articles, catalogs, a copy of The Paris Review, preparatory materials for screen prints; photographic materials which includes a photograph of Elaine de Kooning; and digital video recordings related to works by Poleskie.
  - Address Book, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles re Stephen Poleskie and Chiron Press, 1966-2020; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Associated American Artists, Business Correspondence and Sales Records, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business Ledger, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Catalogs and Exhibition Announcements, 1961-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Catalogs and Exhibition Announcements, 1965, 1983, 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
  - Chiron Press, Certificate of Discontinuance of Business, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chiron Press, Transfer of Ownership, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings re Stephen Poleskie and Chiron Press, 1965-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, and Checklists for Benefits and Fundraisers, 1963-1975, 2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, Bank Statements and Check Stubs, 1964-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Flying, Parts 1 and 2, 2003; Archival Resource Key; 2 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Holiday Postcards, 1963, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interview with Stephen Poleskie, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jackie Fine Arts, Inc., Option Purchase Agreements, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Stephen Poleskie, 1965-1967, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Also includes a photograph of Elaine de Kooning and Nick Kruschnik.
  - Print Work Invitations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1962-2014, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ralph Hughes' Shaftway, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Richard Feigen Graphics, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sales Records, 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sales Records, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Bird Film, 1966; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Paris Review 78, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Paris Review, Business Correspondence, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - The Paris Review, Preparatory Materials, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wilderness Art Mtq. Co., Business Certificate, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Writings by Stephen Poleskie, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)